<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="meeting-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochem Soc Trans</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">bst</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BST</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biochemical Society Transactions</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0300-5127</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-8752</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19021508</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2652831</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bst0361120</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST0361120</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biochemical Society Focused Meetings</subject></subj-group><series-title>Transition Metals in Biochemistry</series-title><series-text>A joint Biochemical Society meeting with the Inorganic Biochemistry Discussion Group to honour Professor Andrew Thomson FRS, held at University of East Anglia, Norwich, U.K., 24&#x02013;26 June 2008. Organized and Edited by Steve Chapman (Edinburgh, U.K.), David Richardson (University of East Anglia, U.K.) and Nick Watmough (University of East Anglia, U.K.).</series-text></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exploring the mechanism of tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">Transition Metals in Biochemistry</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Biochemical Society Transactions (2008) Volume 36, part 6</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thackray</surname><given-names>Sarah&#x000a0;J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mowat</surname><given-names>Christopher&#x000a0;G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>Stephen&#x000a0;K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="A1">EastCHEM, School of Chemistry, University of Edinburgh, West Mains Road, Edinburgh EH9 3JJ, U.K.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><sup>1</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed (email <email>S.K.Chapman@ed.ac.uk</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>36</volume><issue>Pt 6</issue><fpage>1120</fpage><lpage>1123</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2008 The Author(s) The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The haem proteins TDO (tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase) and IDO (indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase) are specific and powerful oxidation catalysts that insert one molecule of dioxygen into <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan in the first and rate-limiting step in the kynurenine pathway. Recent crystallographic and biochemical analyses of TDO and IDO have greatly aided our understanding of the mechanisms employed by these enzymes in the binding and activation of dioxygen and tryptophan. In the present paper, we briefly discuss the function, structure and possible catalytic mechanism of these enzymes.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="kwd"><kwd>haem</kwd><kwd>indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase</kwd><kwd>kynurenine</kwd><kwd>oxygen</kwd><kwd>tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="abbr"><kwd>IDO, indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase</kwd><kwd>hIDO, <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> IDO</kwd><kwd>TDO, tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase</kwd><kwd>rmTDO, <italic>Ralstonia metallidurans</italic> TDO</kwd><kwd>xcTDO, <italic>Xanthomonas campestris</italic> TDO</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><ref-count count="19"/><page-count count="4"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Haem-containing proteins have a wide variety of functions ranging from oxygen transport, storage and activation to simple single-electron transfers. TDO (tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase) and IDO (indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase) are members of a small family of haem enzymes that catalyse the aerobic metabolism of <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan to <italic>N</italic>-formylkynurenine. TDO was initially discovered in the 1930s and is found in both eukaryotes and prokaryotes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. TDO expression is normally restricted to the liver in mammals, although it has been identified in the brain and epididymis of some species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. IDO was first isolated from rabbit intestine in 1967 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], and is found in many eukaryotes where it is expressed ubiquitously throughout the body, except in the liver. Some prokaryotic IDO-like proteins from <italic>Shewanella</italic> species have been identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], but to date these have no known function.</p><p>Sequence similarity between family members is low, with amino acid sequence alignment indicating an identity of approx. 10% between family members. Homology is only apparent from their three-dimensional structures and the conservation of certain amino acids in their active sites.</p></sec><sec><title>Why are TDO and IDO of interest?</title><sec><title>A vital biochemical reaction</title><p>TDO and IDO activate molecular oxygen and catalyse its insertion into <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan to form <italic>N</italic>-formylkynurenine, in the first and rate-limiting step in the kynurenine pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The kynurenine pathway processes over 90% of <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan utilized by humans. Although both enzymes catalyse the same reaction, TDO is highly substrate-specific, only dioxygenating <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan and some tryptophan derivatives substituted in the 5- and 6-positions. IDO displays wider substrate specificity, catalysing the dioxygenation of <sc>D</sc>-tryptophan, tryptamine and 5-hydroxytryptamine (serotonin) in addition to those substrates dioxygenated by TDO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Tryptophan regulation</title><p>Both TDO and IDO play a central role in the regulation of tryptophan in the human body, controlling the kynurenine pathway and influencing serotogenic regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. IDO and TDO activity alters local tryptophan concentration and the build-up of pathway metabolites can lead to numerous physiological and pathophysiological conditions. These include cataract formation, AIDS-related dementia and ischaemic brain injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. In addition, the local depletion of tryptophan by IDO or TDO is associated with an antimicrobial response. Some pathogens are sensitive to tryptophan degradation, and this may be an effective mechanism for controlling their ability to proliferate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Immune regulation</title><p>Although both enzymes catalyse the same reaction, compartmentalization of IDO and TDO expression is thought to reflect their differing biological roles. IDO plays an active role in the human body's immune response, but there is little evidence to suggest that TDO plays a part in this process. Immune regulation by IDO is extremely complex, but two major roles have become evident [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. First, IDO is a normal effector of peripheral tolerance in the immunoregulatory pathway of tryptophan metabolism. It helps to create an appropriate immune response, influencing the balance between tolerance and attack. Secondly, it is thought to play an essential role in acquired immune tolerance. IDO helps tumours to induce tolerance from the host's immune system by interacting with T-cells and depleting <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], and it has consequently emerged as an attractive drug target in cancer and transplant treatments.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>TDO and IDO structures?</title><sec><title>Overall structure</title><p>Recent crystallographic studies of xcTDO (<italic>Xanthomonas campestris</italic> TDO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], rmTDO (<italic>Ralstonia metallidurans</italic> TDO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and hIDO (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic> IDO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] have aided our understanding of this family of haem enzymes. The crystal structures of xcTDO and rmTDO are essentially identical, sharing 47% sequence identity, and are intimately associated homotetrameric enzymes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>a). They are perhaps best described as a dimer of dimers because the N-terminal residues of each monomer form part of the substrate-binding site in an adjacent monomer. The N-terminal region lies above the distal face of the haem, providing part of the binding cavity. The proteins are completely helical, and a flexible loop (comprising residues 250&#x02013;260 of xcTDO), involved in <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan binding, is observed just outside the haem pocket. This loop is only ordered in crystals grown in the presence of <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan, as substrate binding appears to induce its ordering.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Structures of (<bold>a</bold>) xcTDO and (<bold>b</bold>) hIDO</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Structure of xcTDO. <sc>L</sc>-Tryptophan is shown in red, haem is grey, and separate monomers are shown in cyan, magenta, grey and blue. (<bold>b</bold>) Structure of hIDO. Haem is shown in grey, the smaller N-terminal domain is shown in grey, and the larger C-terminal domain is shown in marine.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bst401i001"/></fig><p>IDO is a monomeric protein, folded into two distinct domains: a large (C-terminal) domain and a small (N-terminal) capping domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>b). Contact between these domains is extensive, and they are joined by a long loop. The larger domain is essentially topologically identical with a monomer of TDO, and the structures are readily superposable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. The loop region connecting the two domains provides similar interactions in the active site to those provided by the N-terminal arm of TDO, forming part of the active-site cavity. A flexible loop exists just outside the haem pocket, like that of TDO, but is not fully resolved crystallographically, probably due to the lack of bound substrate in the active site.</p></sec><sec><title>Active-site environment</title><p>TDO and IDO are <italic>b</italic>-type haem proteins with histidine occupying the axial co-ordination position to the haem iron. The only structure available with substrate bound at the active site in the catalytically active ferrous state is xcTDO. The structure clearly shows the important substrate-binding interactions in the active site. The active-site pockets of xcTDO with and without <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan bound and that of hIDO are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. Owing to high similarity between the active sites of TDO and IDO, it is reasonable to assume a similar substrate-binding mode in IDO. Interactions of the substrate with the active site can be split into two categories: interactions with the carboxy and ammonium groups of <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan, and those with the indole ring system.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Active-site residues of xcTDO and hIDO</title><p>Active-site residues of (<bold>a</bold>) substrate-free xcTDO, (<bold>b</bold>) <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan-bound xcTDO, with <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan shown in red, and (<bold>c</bold>) hIDO, with 4-phenylimidazole (shown in red) bound.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bst401i002"/></fig><p>In the structure of xcTDO, the carboxy group of <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan interacts with Arg<sup>117</sup>, Tyr<sup>113</sup> and Thr<sup>254</sup>. Amino acid residues equivalent to Arg<sup>117</sup> and Tyr<sup>113</sup> are found in nearly all TDO and IDO proteins. This carboxy-binding motif appears to be essential for substrate binding; arginine reorients in the presence of substrate, co-ordinating the carboxy group of <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan with both &#x02018;open&#x02019; and &#x02018;closed&#x02019; conformations observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>a and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>b). The closed conformation is only observed in TDO crystals grown in the presence of <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan. The substrate ammonium group is hydrogen-bonded to the side-chain hydroxy group of Thr<sup>254</sup>, the 7-propionate group of the haem, and a water molecule. Thr<sup>254</sup> is involved in binding both the ammonium and carboxy moieties of <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan and is part of the flexible loop, just outside the haem pocket.</p><p>The substrate indole ring binds into a hydrophobic pocket, where it interacts with the side chain of Phe<sup>51</sup> and several other hydrophobic residues, including Tyr<sup>24</sup> and Tyr<sup>27</sup> from the adjacent monomer. Both of these tyrosine residues are hydrogen-bonded to a glutamate residue, linking the N-terminal loop of the adjacent monomer to the active site, and this Tyr-Glu motif is conserved throughout TDO and IDO proteins.</p><p>Perhaps the most obvious difference between the active sites of TDO and IDO is the presence of His<sup>55</sup> in xcTDO and its equivalent, Ser<sup>167</sup> in hIDO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). In TDO, the histidine side chain is hydrogen-bonded with the NH group of the indole ring of <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan, and a role for His<sup>55</sup> would appear to be in regulating substrate binding. In comparison, Ser<sup>167</sup> in IDO is incapable of forming this bond, and it appears unlikely that this residue plays any critical role in substrate binding or catalysis by IDO.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>What is the catalytic mechanism?</title><sec><title>Substrate binding</title><p>The proposed catalytic mechanism employed by this family of enzymes is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>. It is thought that the ferrous enzyme is required for catalytic activity and, upon substrate binding, there is an increase in the electrochemical midpoint potential for both TDO and IDO. This shift in the reduction potential reflects additional stabilization of the ferrous form.Such a thermodynamic stabilization of the reduced form would clearly favour reduction before substrate binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. A recent study has suggested that cytochrome <italic>b</italic><sub>5</sub> is the electron transfer partner for IDO, providing ferrous active protein <italic>in vivo</italic>, consistent with these results.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Proposed catalytic mechanism of IDO and TDO</title><p>Initial formation of the ternary complex (<bold>1</bold>) occurs by substrate binding to the ferrous protein, followed by dioxygen binding. The ternary complex activates O<sub>2</sub> and catalysis proceeds via the formation of a hydroperoxide intermediate (<bold>2</bold> and <bold>5</bold>) that undergoes either a Criegee or a dioxetane rearrangement to form the product <italic>N</italic>-formylkynurenine (<bold>7</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bst401i003"/></fig><p>For TDO, the initial formation of the ternary complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, <bold>1</bold>) occurs by substrate binding followed by dioxygen binding to the ferrous protein. For IDO, the order of binding events is more complex, but the ternary complex must still be formed before the reaction can proceed. The ternary complex activates O<sub>2</sub> and allows the otherwise spin-forbidden reaction to proceed.</p></sec><sec><title>Formation of the hydroperoxide intermediate</title><p>It has been proposed that formation of the hydroperoxide intermediate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, <bold>2</bold> and <bold>5</bold>) is catalysed by the loss of the indole proton. Two mechanisms are thought to be probable: base-catalysed deprotonation or proton abstraction by bound dioxygen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. If the substrate-binding mode in IDO is similar to that seen in xcTDO, proton abstraction by a proteinaceous base is only possible in TDO, with the active-site histidine (His<sup>55</sup> in xcTDO) being the only basic residue in the active site of either enzyme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). However, catalytic activity is maintained upon substitution of alanine for His<sup>55</sup> in xcTDO, suggesting that base-catalysed deprotonation may not be essential for enzymatic activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Catalysis by the iron-bound dioxygen is generally proposed for IDO in the absence of a base, and seems reasonable from modelling simulations.</p></sec><sec><title>Rearrangement of the hydroperoxide intermediate</title><p>The rearrangement of the hydroperoxide intermediate to form the product could occur via either a Criegee or a dioxetane intermediate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Little biochemical information currently exists to discriminate between these two differing pathways, and all discussion has been based on thermodynamic considerations and computer modelling simulations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Thermodynamic considerations indicate that formation of the highly strained dioxetane intermediate and its high exothermicity of decomposition make this an unlikely route to be employed by an enzyme. In addition, no chemiluminescence has been detected on decomposition of the dioxetane. These data alone support the Criegee rearrangement for both IDO and TDO. However, further investigation is necessary to determine the nature of this rearrangement.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Recent crystallographic and biochemical analyses of TDO and IDO have aided our understanding of the mechanisms employed for binding and activating dioxygen by allowing identification of key active-site residues. Analysis of the active-site pockets of TDO and IDO shows that there are differences in the choice of residues employed in catalysis. However, how these changes have an impact on the catalytic mechanism and reaction intermediates employed by these enzymes is still unclear. Recent studies have led to possible future routes of investigation. These include: substitution of newly identified key active-site residues to identify their roles in catalysis; EPR and ENDOR (electron nuclear double resonance) studies of reaction intermediates, and computer modelling simulations.</p></sec><sec><title>Note added in proof (received 23 September 2008)</title><p>In a recent article by Chung et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], density functional theory calculations on the catalytic mechanism of TDO and IDO have cast doubt on the relevance of the Criegee mechanism and raised the possibility of a radical addition pathway.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the Wellcome Trust for financial support.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kotake</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masayama</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The intermediary metabolism of tryptophan. XVIII. The mechanism of formation of kynurenine from tryptophan</article-title><source>Z. Physiol. Chem.</source><year>1936</year><volume>243</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>244</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishiguro</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skin <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan-2,3-dioxygenase and rat hair growth</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1993</year><volume>329</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8354392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessette</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulihan-Giblin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durcan</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase RNA in rodent brain</article-title><source>J. Neurochem.</source><year>1993</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1159</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7679723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayaishi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tryptophan pyrrolase of rabbit intestine: <sc>D</sc>- and <sc>L</sc>-tryptophan-cleaving enzyme or enzymes</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1967</year><volume>242</volume><fpage>5260</fpage><lpage>5266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6065097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forouhar</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J.L.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mowat</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vorobiev</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abashidze</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruckmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thackray</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seetharaman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular insights into substrate recognition and catalysis by tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17197414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tankiewicz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pawlak</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buczko</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzymes of the kynurenine pathway</article-title><source>Postepy Hig. Med. Dosw.</source><year>2001</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11795205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sono</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roach</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulter</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heme-containing oxygenases</article-title><source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>1996</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>2841</fpage><lpage>2887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11848843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wirleitner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neurauter</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrocksnadel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frick</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interferon-&#x003b3;-induced conversion of tryptophan: immunologic and neuropsychiatric aspects</article-title><source>Curr. Med. Chem.</source><year>2003</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1581</fpage><lpage>1591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12871129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>A.-G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection and clinical significance of kynurenine</article-title><source>Guowai Yixue Linchuang Shengwu Huaxue Yu Jianyanxue Fence</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>835</fpage><lpage>837</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuta</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takemura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seishima</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in quinolinic acid production and its related enzymes following <sc>D</sc>-galactosamine and lipopolysaccharide-induced hepatic injury</article-title><source>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</source><year>2004</year><volume>428</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15246871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heseler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daubener</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase in antimicrobial defense and immunoregulation: tryptophan depletion versus production of toxic kynurenines</article-title><source>Curr. Drug Metab.</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17430112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munn</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase, tumor-induced tolerance and counter-regulation</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Immunol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16460921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mellor</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munn</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keskin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jhaver</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baban</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tryptophan catabolism and T cell responses</article-title><source>Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>527</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15206713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bale</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ealick</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure and mechanism of tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase, a heme enzyme involved in tryptophan catabolism and in quinolinate biosynthesis</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2007</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17198384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsuki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hino</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiro.</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of human indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase: catalytic mechanism of O<sub>2</sub> incorporation by a heme-containing dioxygenase</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>2611</fpage><lpage>2616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16477023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basran</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafice</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Efimov</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheesman</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghamsari</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A kinetic, spectroscopic, and redox study of human tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>4752</fpage><lpage>4760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18370401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papadopoulou</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mewies</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seward</surname><given-names>H.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Svistunenko</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redox and spectroscopic properties of human indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase and a His303Ala variant: implications for catalysis</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>14318</fpage><lpage>14328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16245948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iizuka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishimura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><sc>L</sc>-Tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase; structure, function and interaction with substrate</article-title><source>Dev. Biochem.</source><year>1980</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>187</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiro</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morokuma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Density functional theory study on a missing piece in understanding of heme chemistry: the reaction mechanism for indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase and tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2008</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>12299</fpage><lpage>12309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18712870</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>